<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mackenzie K. Brooks</title>
    <description>Academic librarian. Interests: Digital Humanities, the promise of linked data, the myth of the digital native, questioning the book as object, feminism, and rejecting the cult of busy. 
</description>
    <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 11:34:22 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 11:34:22 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Real Talk on Static Sites and Digital Literacies</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The following is the lightly edited script from my TechConnect presentation at ACRL 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1tTBsuim_Lr9bLgvMOsO4Xwy9f3sRafMeSoQa_a3_Lhs/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;The slides are available&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone, my name is Mackenzie Brooks and I’m an Associate Professor and Digital Humanities Librarian at Washington and Lee University. I’m here today to talk about static site generators and digital literacies. I’ve titled this presentation “real talk” because I think there are some gaps in the ways we talk about the use of these tools in digital scholarship, especially when it comes to instruction. My plan for the next 20 minutes is to talk about the what/why of static site generators, share some examples from the digital scholarship world and case studies from my own projects, then discuss ways that the conversation around these tools needs to expand include curriculum, instruction, and digital pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are static sites? You may be wondering, did we make it all the way through Web 2.0 just to come back to basic hand-coded websites? Not quite. The rise in popularity of static sites has come about thanks to what’s known as “static site generators.” These generators use templates, metadata, and content expressed in Markdown to generate a set of HTML/CSS/JS files necessary for your site, which are then uploaded to a server. We can compare static sites to dynamic ones where the content is generated by the web application when the web page is called, usually a database is involved. Static sites are completely built before they’re made live or accessed on the Web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just so you can see an example of what this looks like, here is a screen cap of my text editor when I’m working on a blog post on my personal website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The folders labeled &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_includes&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_layouts&lt;/code&gt; have snippets of code and templates that tell each page where to put the content. For example, I can write code for the footer of my website once, then simply say “include footer.html” in the page layout template. In the middle you see my post and at the top you can see the YAML metadata. Maybe I don’t want the footer to show up on the pages that hold my blog posts, so I could alter the layout for this post to remove the footer or point to another snippet of code. I can even add as many metadata fields as I want to this post so they can be called in different ways. When I’m ready to update the site, I run a build command in the command line, and all the files are generated into the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; folder, which I can then push to their final location on server somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why might you want to use a static site? Well, one of the main attractions is their lightweight and minimal nature. My personal website takes up 4MB vs. an empty WordPress installation that takes up 60MB. This is a lighter load both for the administrator/creator of the site, as well as the end user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the digital scholarship world, the term “minimal computing” has emerged to describe this attention to resource constraints. You can learn more about Minimal Computing by visiting this website created by a subgroup of the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO). There will also be a future issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly devoted to minimal computing and I will share my bibliography. While this is not a presentation about minimal computing specifically, I do want to be clear that minimal computing is asking these questions from a lens of social justice and from the perspective of those doing DH in the Global South. This is not just minimalism for minimalism’s sake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am hoping you can imagine the trickle down benefits of sites using this technology. Not only are these sites lighter, but they might be easier to scale, to sustain, and to preserve. There are numerous static site generators so you can choose one that compliments the languages or tools you’re already using. Static sites lend themselves to the kind of practices we like to encourage in digital scholarship - version control, structured data, separation of form and content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, static sites are being touted as a vehicle for teaching digital skills and promoting digital literacies. And while I completely agree with this point, this is what I want to come back to later in my presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, I wanted to give some examples of how static site projects are being used in and outside of the digital scholarship world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many of you may be familiar with the Programming Historian, which is a Jekyll based based site for hosting tutorials on digital scholarship methods. Their entire peer review system is run through GitHub, though its editors have admitted that the relatively high technical fluency requirements can be a barrier for editors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next we have Ed, a Jekyll theme that has been designed to display digital editions. I didn’t feature it here, but there is also Wax, a digital collections and exhibit platform built on similar methods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collection Builder is another digital exhibits tool coming out of the University of Idaho. It’s designed to import a spreadsheet of digital collections metadata and generate a site that can be pushed to GitHub Pages etc. And I will give them credit for their documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally, for an example beyond digital scholarship, we have Vote.gov. The 18F group out of the GSA works to redesign agency websites, often using static site generators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a short list, but there are many other examples, including Open Educational Resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for as awesome as these static site generators are, they are not without a learning curve. I made this list of skills that you would need to be able to launch a static site using a static site generator. This is a lot of things! If you work in library technology or in digital scholarship, maybe this list seems reasonable to you. But if you are outside those groups, I would argue that this is a tremendous amount of things to learn if your goal is to launch a personal website, digital exhibit, or project site. Especially when we compare it to the ease of using something like Wordpress or dare I say it, SquareSpace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this slide I’ve thrown up the Bryn Mawr Digital Competencies, which is my go-to framework for digital literacies. I’m not going to try to make individual connections between these two lists, but I think you can use static site generators to address any of these competencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to the “real talk” part of this presentation. Static site generators as a vehicle for teaching digital literacy skills are great! Before I go any further, I want you to know that I fully endorse this and have had it validated in my personal experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I think it is a disservice to digital pedagogy and anyone who might be conducting these projects in a collaborative environment to merely gesture at these literacies, the way that most of the rhetoric around static sites tends to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As librarians, we may have learned most of these skills on our own through trial and error, through Googling, or through our predecessor’s hodge podge documentation. And if we’re being honest, we probably enjoyed the learning process. But our collaborative partners in digital scholarship projects, our faculty/students/staff/community members are learning from us, the librarians. We are the ones responsible for teaching these skills as DH or DS librarians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent a lot of energy on information literacy instruction. And as DH/DS Librarians, we have started to think more deeply about the ways we do our work. I am reminded of the “Beyond Buttonology” article by John Russell and Merinda Kaye Hensley from 2017. They remind us that DH work should not be isolated from our work as information literacy instructors. A recent issue of DH+Lib has also looked at these connections between the Framework and DH projects. We know that we need to do more than just teach people where to click - we want to do more than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what concerns me about the rise of static site generators in digital scholarship projects is that we often see lip service to these literacies without the corresponding attention to the curriculum or instruction necessary to develop these literacies. Moreover, the significant learning curve means that we have to spend a lot of time on the buttonology side of getting these sites running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a screen cap from the Jekyll home page, showing you how easy it is to get up and running “in seconds”. In my experience helping students install Jekyll on their computers, we’re looking at many thousands of seconds. I’ve even waited while one student called their dad to get the admin password to their computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below you’ll see a quote from a software developer in an article title “Using A Static Site Generator At Scale: Lessons Learned” in Smashing Magazine. I bring it to your attention because he’s describing the perspective of the content editors rather than the software developers. In the DH context, the content people are often our faculty and students. We need to acknowledge their perspective and experiences when evaluating and choosing platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static sites are often compared to our go-to platforms like WordPress, Drupal, or Omeka. And sure, all of these platforms are weightier than a static site and require someone to administer and update them. But I work with a number of collaborative partners for whom learning these tools is challenging enough. Asking them to write in Markdown or even edit something in GitHub is a lot. But especially in a small institution, these are relationships I value and I’m going to strive to find an approach that works for them. If I decide to recommend a static site for a digital project, it’s because I have evaluated the situation and feel comfortable devoting my time or the team’s time to the necessary and corresponding instruction. A tech stack that falls more in line with our values does not magic away the responsibility we have to our collaborators. Because when we’re the ones responsible for disseminating digital scholarship methods, they are our students and this is a pedagogical relationship, not just a service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his piece on the Minimal Computing Website, Stewart Varner writes, “First, while “minimal computing” may be small in terms of design and server space, It is not necessarily minimal from a labor perspective. What makes a lot of our unsustainable tools so attractive is that lowered the barriers to creating digital projects. If we raise them again, there will be those who will be at least temporarily left out and it probably won’t be wealthy institutions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share this quote with the acknowledgment that I’m presenting from a wealthy institution. I’m also coming from an institution where the library faculty lead a minor in Digital Culture &amp;amp; Information. We have the ability to teach these skills in credit-bearing situations. I have the resources and infrastructure to do this kind of work, but that doesn’t mean that all my collaborative partners now have every single of the of the digital skills I listed earlier. These are long-term projects and they require care and attention for both the tech choices, but more importantly the relationships and the pedagogy of learning together in a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with all being said, now I want to share some quick case studies from the projects that I have been involved with on my campus. All of these projects use Jekyll. Like most DH projects, none of them are finished, but you should be able to easily find the GitHub repositories with our code if you want to see examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we have the Huon d’Auvergne Digital Archive, a digital edition project that presents four Franco-Italian romance epics, encoded in TEI and with the scans presented via IIIF. The overall structure of this site is relatively simple, but the reading interface becomes complex quickly, especially given some of the needs of the scholars involved. I am the main DH collaborator on this project along with the faculty and students. Using Jekyll has helped us avoid using an XML-based web app, instead we rely on JavaScript libraries and we have a lot of control over the behavior of the site (plus we don’t have write anything in XSLT). A lot of this site’s functionality relies on the metadata for each page to link up the scan and text for each folio. The lead faculty member was really interested in learning more of this technology and so I felt like it was reasonable to select a platform that we both could work on together. The faculty member can make most of the edits to the site himself and it’s been really helpful to track all of the work in GitHub. His less technically inclined project partners make issues in GitHub when they notice something that needs fixing. That being said, we do bump up against the limits of Jekyll and are considering other options for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we have the Florence As It Was project. This project is primarily concerned with creating 3-D models of buildings in medieval Florence and reinserting the original artwork. The website serves as a project site and encyclopedia of articles about the people and places they’re studying. Using the metadata in each page, we’re able to tag each article and then use a for loop to find the pages that have been tagged a certain way to sort them into multiple categories in the encyclopedia. This project always has a lot of students working on the site, and not all of them have the technical background or the time to make major changes to the site. However, this site has been deployed using Netlify, a continuous integration service, so students edit the pages directly in GitHub without having to install Jekyll on their computers. This has made a huge difference in our workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last example is one that I have not contributed to myself, however I have multiple students who have completed independent projects using this Jekyll theme. It’s called Flaneur and it’s built by Dawn Childress (UCLA) using Jeykll and Leaflet. It looks great, works really well, and is a great option for mapping projects. It’s easy to tinker with little pieces of this theme to change the look or functionality. Just this week I helped a student alter one option in the Leaflet code to change the way the clustering of pins works. And this is where Jekyll can really shine as a teaching tool - the student is a minor in our program, so he has encountered most of the digital skills he needs, but Jekyll is a great way to take them to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to be clear, these DH projects are long-term and they’re led by the faculty members. I may not have the power to conduct training in the manner or amount that I think is necessary. I would imagine many of us have been in the situation of trying to back seat drive the instruction that we think we need. I’ve also worked on DH projects where the faculty member has been very upfront about not wanting to have to learn the technical pieces, so Jekyll is not something I’ve recommended for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I leave you with a list of a questions. Obviously these are the type of questions to ask before embarking on any type of project. But we can all think of projects that have evolved perhaps more organically than we would like, so this is your reminder to stop and ask yourselves these things before you rush to say yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I do want to end on a note of encouragement. Despite everything I’ve said, I do believe that static sites can be a great vehicle for digital literacy instruction. Believe the hype, just know what you’re getting into. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Becker, Devin, et al. “CollectionBuilder-CONTENTdm: Developing a Static Web ‘Skin’ for CONTENTdm-Based Digital Collections.” The Code4Lib Journal, no. 49, Aug. 2020. Code4Lib Journal, https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/15326.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Childress, Dawn. Re-Imagining the Stack: Minimal Computing at Scale in the Digital Library. https://dawnchildress.com/2016/11/10/dlf16/. Accessed 23 Mar. 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connell, Ruth Sara. “Content Management Systems: Trends in Academic Libraries.” Information Technology and Libraries, vol. 32, no. 2, 2, June 2013, pp. 42–55. ejournals.bc.edu, doi:10.6017/ital.v32i2.4632.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diaz, Chris. “Using Static Site Generators for Scholarly Publications and Open Educational Resources.” The Code4Lib Journal, no. 42, Nov. 2018. Code4Lib Journal, https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/13861.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Digital Competencies. https://www.brynmawr.edu/digitalcompetencies. Accessed 16 Mar. 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly Special Issue on Minimal Computing. http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/submissions/cfps_archive.html.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gil, Alex. “The User, the Learner and the Machines We Make · Minimal Computing.” Minimal Computing, 21 May 2015, https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information Maintenance as a Practice of Care. Zenodo. https://zenodo.org/record/3251131#.YFEvhZkpBpQ. Accessed 16 Mar. 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Newson, Kaitlin. “Tools and Workflows for Collaborating on Static Website Projects.” The Code4Lib Journal, no. 38, Oct. 2017. Code4Lib Journal, https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/12779.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Russell, John E., and Merinda Kaye Hensley. “Beyond Buttonology: Digital Humanities, Digital Pedagogy, and the ACRL Framework.” College and Research Libraries News. crln.acrl.org, doi:https://doi.org/10.5860/crln.78.11.588. Accessed 16 Mar. 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Using A Static Site Generator At Scale: Lessons Learned.” Smashing Magazine, https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2016/08/using-a-static-site-generator-at-scale-lessons-learned/.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Varner, Stewart. “Minimal Computing in Libraries: Introduction · Minimal Computing.” Minimal Computing, 15 Jan. 2017, https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2017/01/15/mincomp-libraries-intro/.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visconti, Amanda, et al. “Running a Collaborative Research Website and Blog with Jekyll and GitHub.” Programming Historian, Nov. 2020. programminghistorian.org, https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/collaborative-blog-with-jekyll-github.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Walsh, Brandon. The Programming Historian and Editorial Process in Digital Publishing · Brandon Walsh. http://walshbr.com/blog/the-programming-historian-and-editorial-process-in-digital-publishing/. Accessed 16 Mar. 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“What Is a Static Site Generator? How Do I Find the Best One to Use?” Netlify, https://www.netlify.com/blog/2020/04/14/what-is-a-static-site-generator-and-3-ways-to-find-the-best-one/?utm_source=jamstackorg&amp;amp;utm_medium=what-are-ssg-pnh&amp;amp;utm_campaign=devex. Accessed 16 Mar. 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Why Static Site Generators Are The Next Big Thing.” Smashing Magazine, https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2015/11/modern-static-website-generators-next-big-thing/.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wikle, Olivia. “What Is Static Web and What’s It Doing in the Digital Humanities Classroom?” Dh Lib, 22 June 2020, https://dhandlib.org/2020/06/22/what-is-static-web-and-whats-it-doing-in-the-digital-humanities-classroom/.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2021/04/14/real-talk-static-sites.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2021/04/14/real-talk-static-sites.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Studies in Bibliography</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I said in my last post, I’m headed off to &lt;a href=&quot;https://rarebookschool.org&quot;&gt;Rare Book School&lt;/a&gt; at UVa next week. I haven’t been before, but I have spent a week at some kind of institute for the last three summers (so far there is a lot more Latin at RBS than at DHSI or HILT). The &lt;a href=&quot;https://rarebookschool.org/courses/general/g55/reading-list/&quot;&gt;recommended reading&lt;/a&gt; for my course, Scholarly Editing: Principles and Practice, is a series of six essays by G. Thomas Tanselle. The series starts in 1975 and continues through 2000, creating a pretty dense snapshot of the scholarly editing conversation during that time. Certainly a 300-page lit review is one way to get up to speed on a field, if only Tanselle didn’t spend most of the time tearing apart everyone else’s arguments while simultaneously accusing them of being too polemical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first essay (1975), Tanselle explains the principles of W. W. Greg’s “The Rationale of Copy-Text,” which are, in my own words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Editors should use restraints and should not rely on purely “ecletic methods.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The last edition published in the author’s lifetime is not automatically the best.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Substantive variants matter more than accidental ones. Because, authors are more likely to concern themselves with substantive changes and copyists etc. with “accidentals.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be reasonable. Know when to use the rules and when not to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanselle then spends the next twenty-five years criticizing other scholars for misunderstanding Greg. While he finds some questions interesting, he claims that most publications do very little to advance the field. In his view, most  scholars are pushing aside Greg and what they see as his preference for authorial intent because of a new focus on the social context of literary production. Tanselle sees these arguments as misguided and spends a lot of saying so - he thinks that Greg still accommodates most of these points of view and that everyone else just doesn’t get it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real myth involved is the belief that intentionalist editing does not accommodate collaborative authorship and textual instability. (SiB vol 49 (1996): 5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 1996, he’s a little less salty and ends by quoting Woolf to illustrate his point - “a novel… exists on the far side of a gulf.” Editors are just trying to reconstruct the whole story from what is ultimately a textual artifact (just like other historical fields). If you get past authorial intent, the question becomes: what’s the point of a critical edition? Tanselle’s answer: “the limitations of artifacts and insatiability of our interest in the past” (60).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I was interested in mentions of the digital, which mostly come up with McGann and Schillingsburg. Tanselle sees digital editions as improving on an often awkward print apparatus or to enable McGann’s “radial reading.” But what struck me from the whole 300 page slog (and it was a big of a slog) was the resonance of textual studies in DH, or even info lit more broadly. DocNow’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DocNow/diffengine&quot;&gt;diffengine&lt;/a&gt; came to mind for instance. If you believe that remediation is a thing and that form informs content, or that authority is constructed and contextual, then you can’t skate past textual studies. We have more tools now for tracking changes to text by whichever contributor, but I can’t imagine there are many who would argue that text is more stable now than it’s ever been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering, Huxley roots for authorial intent while Orwell falls into the post-structuralist camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/cats1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cats1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;that look that cats give&quot; style=&quot; border: 1px solid black;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/cats2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cats2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;that look that cats give&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2019/06/07/studies-in-bibliography.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2019/06/07/studies-in-bibliography.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sabbatical Plans</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today is the first day of my sabbatical! As a library faculty member on a 12-month contract, it is customary for us to get three months of leave in the summer on a five year cycle. For me, this sabbatical comes on the heels of my promotion to associate professor (!). It also marks the first time I have ever had any substantial opportunity to pursue my own research agenda. The nature of my work is very service-oriented. I teach, consult, and contribute to others’ learning, teaching, and research at my university and beyond. Even my publications reflect this direction. So when it came time to propose my sabbatical plans, I basically had to initialize a whole research agenda. It came together pretty easily after a little reflection, but I’m still adjusting to the idea that I am the one propelling my work, rather than other people. I know the opportunity for deep engagement will be beneficial for my professional (and personal) life, but right now it still feels like a major indulgence. I’ll go into my actual plans below, but for now, my top goal seems to be “figure out what it means to be a person on sabbatical.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided to devote my leave time to developing and documenting a model for building digital editions with &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/TEIC/CETEIcean&quot;&gt;CETEIcean&lt;/a&gt;, and potentially &lt;a href=&quot;http://iiif.io/&quot;&gt;IIIF&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve begun this work on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huondauvergne.org&quot;&gt;Huon d’Auvergne Digital Archive&lt;/a&gt;) and I see a lot of promise in its use by others. I expect I will write more about the landscape, but the short version is: I think there’s still value in the TEI and not so much value in everyone learning XSLT to do something with TEI-encoded documents. I want to create an option for folks who don’t have their own developers but are willing to work through some good documentation. I also want to develop a new course on this topic (and maybe another course on something else). For a good dose of theory, I’ll be taking a scholarly editing course at Rare Book School next week. Finally, I’m hoping to use the proceedings for our local historical society as my demo text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I just want to make texts available online in their best possible form. I want this to be easy for scholars, but mostly I want more texts to make it to the public. I could say more, especially about my particular context, but for now let me leave you with a view of my summer office:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/office.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;laptop on table in outdoor setting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2019/06/03/sabbatical-plans.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2019/06/03/sabbatical-plans.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Born Digital Archives in the Undergraduate Classroom</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Alternate title: why blog about teaching when you can just publish a new article for every class?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to share this recent article in one of my favorite journals: Journal of Interactive Technology and Pedagogy. &lt;a href=&quot;https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/born-digital-archives-in-the-undergraduate-classroom/&quot;&gt;Born Digital Archives in the Undergraduate Classroom&lt;/a&gt; is a write-up of my first-year seminar taught in 2018. Through an educational partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive-it.org/&quot;&gt;Archive-It&lt;/a&gt;, students worked to create their own web archive on a topic of their choosing. It was a fun class! The article covers my methods for introducing a first-year audience to archival theory and digital preservation. It’s just a “View from the Field,” so if you’re looking for more detail, I suggest checking out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mackenziekbrooks.gitbooks.io/dh-180-born-digital/content/&quot;&gt;syllabus&lt;/a&gt;. I have no immediate plans to teach it again, but I hope it can inspire others to make use of born-digital archives in their own teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 15:19:19 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2019/03/18/born-digital-archives-article-published.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2019/03/18/born-digital-archives-article-published.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Teaching TEI to Undergraduates article published!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just wanted to drop in and mention the publication of my first real peer-reviewed article: “Teaching TEI to undergraduates: a case study in digital humanities curriculum” in the special issue of &lt;em&gt;College and Undergraduate Libraries&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tandfonline.com/eprint/DdAqRHI8gySCKnvtvmHy/full&quot;&gt;publisher&lt;/a&gt; // &lt;a href=&quot;https://repository.wlu.edu/handle/11021/33912&quot;&gt;open access&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case study describes two iterations of a Digital Humanities (DH) “Studio” course on scholarly text encoding as a model for a DH curriculum at a small liberal arts college. Designed to accompany a three-credit humanities course, the one-credit DH Studios are taught by library faculty. The paired courses share a final project — a digital edition of a short work of literature encoded in the Text Encoding Initiative. The DH Studio creates a methodology-focused environment for students to practice information and digital literacies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflection&quot;&gt;Reflection:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to teaching commitments and that vicious procrastination/perfectionism cycle, I left myself far too little time to write a twenty page article. There were definitely some bleary weekends and evenings in the month of January. I am a slow writer, even on a topic that is essentially just a report. Revisions were minor, so I can apparently produce decent work while bleary, but I hope someday to be able to work well without the pressure of deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one-credit “humanities lab” concept described in this case study is something that we bring up a lot in my DH/liberal arts circles. I wanted to document how the model worked for us in case it’s useful to others. I do still like the concept, but as the administrator says in &lt;em&gt;The History Boys&lt;/em&gt;, “Strange how even the most tragic turn of events generally resolve themselves into questions about the timetable.” Scheduling is hard!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These courses were my first real experiences teaching full courses. I feel like I have learned a lot since then! The inherent iteration is my favorite part of teaching. You have so many chances to make things better, from year to year or week to week. While I find perfectionism to be a problem when writing, I knew that it would be the death of me when teaching. While I tried to make good decisions, I also didn’t beat myself up if/when things didn’t go well. If you’re paying attention, you will learn something every time you’re in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, I taught three sections (4 students each) of DH 190. Each section was totally different and I had to learn to frame material differently based on the vibe of each group. It was a little like A/B testing in the classroom. Sections of four meant I could give each student individual attention, but I still felt pulled in too many directions, especially when dealing with OS/browser issues. Students worked in pairs, but I encouraged them to help each other when one had solved a problem first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t say what the future of this course will be. While undergraduates can “get” TEI, I’m not sure they need to. I could see reworking this course to focus on minimal editions (see Torrent’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://susannalles.com/materials/syllabi/MinimalEditions.html&quot;&gt;syllabus&lt;/a&gt;). Now that I feel capable of teaching git (thanks Brandon Walsh), I think the git/github/Jekyll/Ed stack might be more fun. The pairing of this course with an advanced French lit course meant that we were using TEI as a vehicle to close reading the course texts. Without the pairing, we could work to transcribe documents from Special Collections with students selecting the types of texts that interested them. We’ll see!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2017 08:02:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2017/07/20/teaching-tei-to-undergraduates.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2017/07/20/teaching-tei-to-undergraduates.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Shot Update</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a year and a half since I assumed liaison responsibilities to the English department at MPOW. I won’t claim to have blossomed into the world’s best liaison, but I have been teaching one-shot instruction sessions on a regular basis. If you’ve spent any time in the instruction/information literacy world, then you know that most librarians are not a fan of the one-shot session. I’ve been “victim” to all the usual complaints: bad timing, course materials aren’t shared, limited time, no pre/post assessment, late notice, no stakes in the assignment, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, I could spend more time cultivating my department to take these sessions more seriously. But after the chance to integrate information literacy concepts into full courses via our Digital Humanities curriculum, it makes more sense to invest my time in that form of pedagogy. I’m not going to stop accepting one-shot requests, but I am going to stop expecting more than is reasonable. What can I really accomplish in thirty minutes with first-year writing students? What are the most useful things for students to learn at this point in the semester?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started developing a one-shot presentation, I was fresh off of several meetings about the new ACRL Framework. I had just read David Weinberger’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/966459702&quot;&gt;Too big to know : rethinking knowledge now that the facts aren’t the facts, experts are everywhere, and the smartest person in the room is the room&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. This was all useful context, but I was overwhelmed by material to cover. I attempted to distill Weinberger’s book into a couple concepts that I could share with students, including: 1) filter failure as a mental model for information overload and 2) how the internet changed the storage and retrieval of information and knowledge gatekeepers. I used the “filter failure” idea to encourage the use of filters in whatever database students are using. I used the changing nature of information to explain some of the library’s (ancient in the eyes of students, and let’s be real, myself) organizational principles. I also tried to work in the “information has value” framework by making students guess our annual collections budget (I still do this. They are always blown away.). These concepts were useful for my own thinking, but I struggled to incorporate them into instruction in a non-prescriptive way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I had a spare morning before an afternoon one-shot and decided to redo my entire presentation. First, I reviewed results from a two-question survey I had administered to a few Writing 100 courses last year. The questions were: 1) What is the most confusing thing about the library and 2) What is the most confusing thing about research? Most of the responses to the first question related to how the library and the collection were organized. The answers to the second question were more useful. Students listed a range of concerns: how to get started, how to cite properly, what makes a good source, and my favorite, “I’m scared of plagiarism and getting kicked out.” From these 40+ responses, I determined the most frequently asked questions, sorted them to mirror the research process, then bookended them with some context-setting questions. The results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the academic library?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where do I start?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I know what keywords to use?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I go further?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What makes a good source?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I organize my research?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if I need more help?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized that the FAQ format would be a great way to attempt to encourage student participation. In my presentations, I try to solicit answers to all questions before volunteering my own. This gives students a chance to share knowledge they might have already gained through other classes or experiences. It is also a useful model for dealing with varying levels of student participation. Some classes are chatty and willing to ask/answer questions throughout, others are definitely not. I can also keep this template for upper-level students by modifying my answers for more in-depth research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I’ve used this new slidedeck in a few Writing 100 courses. The presentations feel smoother, more useful, and more interactive. I know I need to find a way to work in assessment, but it’s great to finally have a flexible structure for these class visits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/slides/slides-library-research-faq.html&quot; width=&quot;576&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 12:45:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2017/03/16/one-shot-update.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2017/03/16/one-shot-update.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Library-Faculty Partnerships Enrich Undergraduate Teaching at Washington and Lee</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;[Originally published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diglib.org/archives/11322/&quot;&gt;Digital Library Federation Contribute blog&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu&quot;&gt;DH @ W&amp;amp;L blog&lt;/a&gt;. Co-written with &lt;a href=&quot;https://bmw9t.github.io/&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt;, Digital Humanities Fellow.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wlu.edu&quot;&gt;Washington and Lee University (W&amp;amp;L)&lt;/a&gt; is excited to be a part of the Digital Library Federation’s efforts, particularly as they pertain to promoting digital humanities on liberal arts campuses. The digital humanities initiative at W&amp;amp;L has grown out of longstanding attempts to connect faculty and staff working in related areas across the university. Our primary goal is to foster communication and training among librarians and faculty at all levels of technical skill in the service of encouraging new approaches to digital pedagogy and research methodology. These efforts grow out of two overlapping groups: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/about/digital-humanities-working-group/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Working Group&lt;/a&gt;, a collective of faculty and staff across the university interested in the intersection of information technology and humanities research and teaching, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/about/dhat/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Action Team&lt;/a&gt;, a joint initiative by W&amp;amp;L’s Information Technology Services (ITS) and the University Library that provides day-to-day guidance and training on integrating digital methodologies into faculty teaching and research. By partnering library faculty and staff with teaching faculty, we believe that we can develop undergraduate pedagogy in a way that benefits all participants. We bring digital humanities to bear on a liberal arts context by encouraging faculty research with undergraduate partners, by using digital tools in the classroom as opportunities to promote digital literacy, and by offering new occasions for collaborative teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undergraduates stand to learn a great deal from working on digital humanities projects, and these students offer enormous energy and resources to their adopted teams. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huondauvergne.org/&quot;&gt;Huon d’Auvergne project&lt;/a&gt;, a digital edition being developed at W&amp;amp;L by Professor Stephen P. McCormick, library faculty, and inter-institutional collaborators, offers one such model for collaboration among faculty, students, and staff that collapses traditional pedagogical hierarchies. While students might begin to learn about the project in the classroom, after a semester course in textual encoding they are given the opportunity to work alongside their professor and digital humanities developers in an actual research setting. We encourage students to take ownership of their contributions to the project. Our students present at conferences, appear as co-authors on papers, and list project contributions on their CV. Through support from the office of the Dean of the College and The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, we stimulate such collaborations by offering competitive stipends to both the faculty and students involved. By further funding undergraduate research projects in digital humanities through a fellowship program, we provide training for students to explore their own interests with the same sort of support that we might offer humanities faculty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We carry our support of digital projects and tools in the classroom beyond logistics and mechanics, using them as opportunities to educate students about more traditional information literacy topics. Many of our librarians involved in work with classroom instruction began their careers in cataloging or systems librarianship, but our digital humanities efforts have created a space in which they can translate these experiences into outward-facing pedagogy in metadata, intellectual property, and digital preservation. These teaching opportunities generate collaborations with subject and instruction librarians who already possess extensive training in curriculum design and information literacy instruction. When working with Omeka, for example, our Digital Scholarship Librarian provides students training in digitization, metadata conventions, and sustainability. While the digitization of original material often falls outside the scope of semester-long Omeka projects, she still takes the time to discuss copyright, attribution, and the ethical and legal use of digital materials. These courses often receive joint visits by our Access Services Librarian and Instructional Design Specialist who offer workshops in visual literacy. By dividing labor among related faculty in such a way we leverage expertise in information literacy from a variety of angles and combine them in a rich curriculum for students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our efforts to disperse technical knowledge beyond early adopters, we have been experimenting with different models of collaborative teaching. One such model, the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/initiatives/curriculum/&quot;&gt;DH Studio&lt;/a&gt;,” involves pairing a traditional humanities course with a one-credit lab. The studio courses are taught by library faculty and give students dedicated time and expertise to learn and apply digital methodologies without sacrificing course content. We are also exploring more direct models of co-teaching in which course time and credits are extended to allow for “baked-in” digital methodology and course content. By partnering with French, journalism, and history professors, we have been able to offer courses in medieval French literature and textual encoding, multimedia storytelling and design, and text analysis approaches to histories of British scandal. Such hybrid courses offer students new avenues of study that educate the instructors as well. And by gearing digital assignments toward primary course objectives, we hope to show that digital humanities collaborations, far from detracting from disciplinary material, can actually challenge and enrich them. By working together, in the short term, digital humanities faculty gain disciplinary skills outside their normal area of expertise, and teaching faculty learn digital humanities skills and techniques in which they might not otherwise have training. In the long term, we aim for these same faculty members to develop the skill-sets necessary to teach these same courses and design new offerings without the same level of collaboration and support, allowing library faculty to further develop new courses themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see the library as the natural home for digital humanities initiatives on the liberal arts campus. The expertise of our faculty and staff in digital technologies and information literacy pedagogy, combined with our close relationships with ITS colleagues and concentration on the practical implications of digital scholarship, stands to enrich the undergraduate curriculum. We offer the library to our students as a space where they can meet faculty and staff as collaborators as well as educators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 11:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2016/02/12/library-faculty-partnerships.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2016/02/12/library-faculty-partnerships.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Search Everything</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During the weeks leading up to fall term, my institution puts on something we call “Fall Academy.” Organized by Academic Technologies, faculty and staff gather for various training, refresher, or orientation sessions on technology, pedagogy, and university policies or practices. It is awesome. And exhausting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, in addition to participating in our &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/2015/07/29/day-of-dh-at-fall-academy-2015/&quot;&gt;Day of DH&lt;/a&gt;, I led a session called “Search Everything.” Nominally this was about our using our discovery layer (Search Everything being the label we use on the library website), but I decided to take a broader approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resetting expectations was my main motivation for this talk. I’m afraid I may have come off too harsh or defensive, but I was not going to stand for any card catalog nostalgia. It’s a complex world out there for information seekers. “Too big to know” as David Weinberger says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My secondary motivation was to remind attendees that their students have almost always lived in a world where Google exists. I might be the youngest “professor” on campus, so sometimes I find myself in this role of Millennial ambassador or translator. I used this presentation to tell the “adults” about student research habits and challenges, primarily through data from &lt;a href=&quot;http://projectinfolit.org/&quot;&gt;Project Information Literacy&lt;/a&gt;. I also walked them through what I tell students about the very recent history of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope it was a useful talk. It was hard to prepare knowing that the audience would bring a wide range of experience. If nothing else, attendees learned to put search terms in quotes except in Google where you have to use Verbatim search, because Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.slides.com/mackenziekbrooks/search-everything/embed&quot; width=&quot;576&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 05:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2015/09/06/search-everything.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2015/09/06/search-everything.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ALA Annual 2015 + FAST</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Again with the time delay, but today is an out-of-office writing day and this blog post is my warm up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my third ALA Annual Conference and I think I’m finally getting the hang of things. I chose better sessions, spent and reserved energy appropriately, and finally brought a Bluetooth iPad keyboard for effective tweeting. I always seem to attend ALA in a transitional job state, and this visit was no different. As of July 1 (during ALA mind you), I am Digital Humanities Librarian at MPOW. I’m thrilled about the change, but it meant I needed to look outside of my normal ALCTS programming to build my schedule. I concentrated on anything with “linked data” in the title. Major points to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://alaac15.ala.org/node/28856&quot;&gt;Amber Billey and and Allison Jai O’Dell&lt;/a&gt; for convering the topic with enthusiasm and to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lib.montana.edu/~jason/talks/ala2015-linked-data-discovery.pdf&quot;&gt;Jason Clark&lt;/a&gt; for making a vendor session bearable. I supplemented my schedule with sessions from folks I know and trust, including Sarah Hovde talking about &lt;a href=&quot;http://alaac15.ala.org/node/29193&quot;&gt;cataloging education&lt;/a&gt; (turn[s out, some people actually get on the job cataloging training, how nice for them), Annie Pho on &lt;a href=&quot;http://alaac15.ala.org/node/28722&quot;&gt;#critlib&lt;/a&gt;, Erin Leach leading &lt;a href=&quot;http://alaac15.ala.org/node/29217&quot;&gt;Creative Ideas in Technical Services”&lt;/a&gt; and Eric Phetteplace (okay Eric was just my LITA Happy Hour buddy). I always try to check out one or two sessions from the big name speaker series, except somehow this year I missed Gloria Steinham and Nick Offerman. It’s nice to be reminded by someone famous that the work you’re doing is important and valued, even if most of their experience is with children’s librarians. It can be hard to sustain interest and enthusiasm for Monday sessions, but they ended up being the best of the whole conference thanks to an amazing talk by &lt;a href=&quot;http://ase.tufts.edu/crlr/team/wolf.htm&quot;&gt;Maryanne Wolf&lt;/a&gt; on deep reading in the digital age (for once, I was not enraged by this topic) and a stellar panel on contexutalizing Omeka exhibits by the folks behind the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ldhi.library.cofc.edu&quot;&gt;Lowcountry Digital History Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below you’ll find the slides from my presentation at the Faceted Subject Access Interest Group. It was a seven minute lightning talk and fortunately for you the slides below do not contain any of the jokes I made that fell flat in the room. The jist: we’ve spent the last two years implementing ArchivesSpace and we’ve made the decision to rely solely OCLC’s FAST headings for subject access points. The FAST headings complement ArchivesSpace’s SOLR indexing and they’re easy for Special Collections staff to apply. Since they’re available to download in several formats, it is fairly easy to get them into ArchivesSpace in batch. So far we’ve only added the topical headings. I want to add the geographic headings, but I have yet to learn enough XSLT to only pull out the Virginia headings. Because ArchivesSpace only displays subjects in the public interface when they’ve been attached to the record, it is not a problem to have 400k topical headings in the staff interface. We will delete headings that we encounter that seem totally irrelevant, though we’ve kept the “that’s what she said jokes” heading just in case. The panel went really well, the rest of the presentations can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;http://connect.ala.org/node/242549&quot;&gt;ALAConnect&lt;/a&gt;, though the audience really only seemed concerned with the FAST headings in their OPAC (the OPAC is dead, long live the OPAC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/mackenziekbrooks/speeding-up-archival-description-with-fast/embed&quot; width=&quot;576&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On location: San Francisco is amazing. I could never live there, in part because I think I’m done with urban life for now, but it was an ideal location for the conference and subsequent vacation. The convention center was easy to get around and had a lovely park on its roof, complete with fountains and ethnic fast food. There were plenty of places to eat and transportation was easy (I’m looking at you Chicago and Anaheim). I witnessed Pride and SCOTUS decision parties, again, way better than a Black Hawks rally (ahem Chicago). Brewster Kahle led a tour of the Internet Archive. Matthew Battles showed us &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i0RVSZ_yDjs&quot;&gt;“Toute la mémoire du monde”&lt;/a&gt; and Harvard verison, &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/116603551&quot;&gt;“Cold Storage.”&lt;/a&gt; There was a JMW Turner exhibit at the de Young. The weather, the parks, the plants, the food was all so great that it didn’t matter that I came down with a cold and had a terrible reaction to antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sometimes encounter librarians who have never been to ALA and it prompts me to consider why I continue to go. I don’t disagree that local/regional events are better in the cost/benefit department, but there is something about particpating on a national level that feels important. It gets you out of your insular library world, even if you all you do is complain about LibGuides with someone from another state. I’m not sure it shapes my professional identity so much as help it get in shape. And now that I’ve started to use a running metaphor, I think this post is over.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2015 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2015/08/03/ala-annual-2015-fast.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2015/08/03/ala-annual-2015-fast.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>#thatcampVA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend* I attended my second THATCamp. But before I talk about how wonderful it was, I want to spend a moment on my first THATCamp. It was the fall of 2011 and I had just finished up my MLIS program. I was working as a library assistant in a health sciences library, so my only outlet for DH-type work was a now-defunct project with my grad student boyfriend. Like most of grad school, it’s embarrassing to recall in much detail, but the theoretical goal was an online encyclopedia/wiki on “Literary Darwinism.”** In reality, it was a project that gave me an excuse to learn Drupal and gave some of my academically-minded friends a research project while they decided if grad school was actually a good idea. We took this project to THATCamp, proposed a session, and people showed up. Some of them even took us seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The culture of acceptance is one of the best parts of THATCamp. As someone with a “healthy” dose of imposter syndrome, conferences are often demoralizing in that still-so-many-things-to-learn way. But THATCamp produces these amazing positive “I’m learning so much!” feelings. There are a lot of reasons for this, but one of my favorites is the decentralization of authority. Experts and novices and everyone in between sit in the same circle to discuss a topic. You could be the most experienced person in the room at one session, or a total n00b at the next. Obviously, I’m not suggesting comparing yourself to others, but the interdisciplinary format encourages this kind of metacognitive assessment of your own skills and expertise. For instance, while we were discussing our project’s infrastructure, someone suggested that we use Weebly because it would be easy and Drupal is hard. I bristled at this in the moment. It was a reasonable suggestion, but I didn’t like the implication that I couldn’t handle Drupal. I knew I was capable of more than just a drag and drop interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward four years. I now have several years of professional experience as a metadata librarian, with at least one spent actively working in the DH world. I am comfortable participating (finally!). And I got to play the role of THATCamp veteran to the three colleagues who accompanied me. It was so gratifying to see their positive reactions to the experience. The romance languages faculty member was delighted to realize that a conference could be more than just listening to some academic read their paper. During the first session he met someone with considerable TEI experience and by the end of the day, we were in a TEI specific session having a meaningful and useful conversation. My librarian colleague went home inspired to ignite a few smoldering projects. We were able to bring a student along. She was brand new to DH, but totally held her own in every session. She wasn’t afraid to ask questions or share her opinion. We ended up in one session explaining how social media works to well-tenured professors. I hope it was a nice send-off for her, she’s now graduated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a final note, I read &lt;a href=&quot;http://libraryjuicepress.com/feminist-pedagogy.php&quot;&gt;Feminist Pedagogy for Library Instruction&lt;/a&gt; the same month as THATCamp Va, and the two complemented each other well. In addition to (or because of?) the aforementioned decentralized authority, women represented a large portion of the attendees, making it feel even less like a typical tech conference. Its open, productive, and collaborative qualities are all things I’d like to bring to my own teaching of technology, so it was helpful to actually experience those things in between terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So get yourself off to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://thatcamp.org/&quot;&gt;THATCamp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Please ignore the time gap between writing and publishing. I know it feels like decades in internet time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** Presented without comment: &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Darwinian_literary_studies&quot;&gt;the Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; on Literary Darwinism as written by Joseph Carroll, expert in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2015/05/31/thatcampva.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2015/05/31/thatcampva.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
