<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mackenzie K. Brooks</title>
    <description>Academic librarian. Interests: Digital Humanities, the promise of linked data, the myth of the digital native, questioning the book as object, feminism, and rejecting the cult of busy. 
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 15:52:40 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 15:52:40 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Studies in Bibliography</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I said in my last post, I’m headed off to &lt;a href=&quot;https://rarebookschool.org&quot;&gt;Rare Book School&lt;/a&gt; at UVa next week. I haven’t been before, but I have spent a week at some kind of institute for the last three summers (so far there is a lot more Latin at RBS than at DHSI or HILT). The &lt;a href=&quot;https://rarebookschool.org/courses/general/g55/reading-list/&quot;&gt;recommended reading&lt;/a&gt; for my course, Scholarly Editing: Principles and Practice, is a series of six essays by G. Thomas Tanselle. The series starts in 1975 and continues through 2000, creating a pretty dense snapshot of the scholarly editing conversation during that time. Certainly a 300-page lit review is one way to get up to speed on a field, if only Tanselle didn’t spend most of the time tearing apart everyone else’s arguments while simultaneously accusing them of being too polemical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first essay (1975), Tanselle explains the principles of W. W. Greg’s “The Rationale of Copy-Text,” which are, in my own words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Editors should use restraints and should not rely on purely “ecletic methods.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The last edition published in the author’s lifetime is not automatically the best.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Substantive variants matter more than accidental ones. Because, authors are more likely to concern themselves with substantive changes and copyists etc. with “accidentals.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be reasonable. Know when to use the rules and when not to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanselle then spends the next twenty-five years criticizing other scholars for misunderstanding Greg. While he finds some questions interesting, he claims that most publications do very little to advance the field. In his view, most  scholars are pushing aside Greg and what they see as his preference for authorial intent because of a new focus on the social context of literary production. Tanselle sees these arguments as misguided and spends a lot of saying so - he thinks that Greg still accommodates most of these points of view and that everyone else just doesn’t get it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real myth involved is the belief that intentionalist editing does not accommodate collaborative authorship and textual instability. (SiB vol 49 (1996): 5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 1996, he’s a little less salty and ends by quoting Woolf to illustrate his point - “a novel… exists on the far side of a gulf.” Editors are just trying to reconstruct the whole story from what is ultimately a textual artifact (just like other historical fields). If you get past authorial intent, the question becomes: what’s the point of a critical edition? Tanselle’s answer: “the limitations of artifacts and insatiability of our interest in the past” (60).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I was interested in mentions of the digital, which mostly come up with McGann and Schillingsburg. Tanselle sees digital editions as improving on an often awkward print apparatus or to enable McGann’s “radial reading.” But what struck me from the whole 300 page slog (and it was a big of a slog) was the resonance of textual studies in DH, or even info lit more broadly. DocNow’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DocNow/diffengine&quot;&gt;diffengine&lt;/a&gt; came to mind for instance. If you believe that remediation is a thing and that form informs content, or that authority is constructed and contextual, then you can’t skate past textual studies. We have more tools now for tracking changes to text by whichever contributor, but I can’t imagine there are many who would argue that text is more stable now than it’s ever been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering, Huxley roots for authorial intent while Orwell falls into the post-structuralist camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/cats1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cats1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;that look that cats give&quot; style=&quot; border: 1px solid black;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/cats2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cats2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;that look that cats give&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2019/06/07/studies-in-bibliography.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2019/06/07/studies-in-bibliography.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sabbatical Plans</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today is the first day of my sabbatical! As a library faculty member on a 12-month contract, it is customary for us to get three months of leave in the summer on a five year cycle. For me, this sabbatical comes on the heels of my promotion to associate professor (!). It also marks the first time I have ever had any substantial opportunity to pursue my own research agenda. The nature of my work is very service-oriented. I teach, consult, and contribute to others’ learning, teaching, and research at my university and beyond. Even my publications reflect this direction. So when it came time to propose my sabbatical plans, I basically had to initialize a whole research agenda. It came together pretty easily after a little reflection, but I’m still adjusting to the idea that I am the one propelling my work, rather than other people. I know the opportunity for deep engagement will be beneficial for my professional (and personal) life, but right now it still feels like a major indulgence. I’ll go into my actual plans below, but for now, my top goal seems to be “figure out what it means to be a person on sabbatical.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided to devote my leave time to developing and documenting a model for building digital editions with &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/TEIC/CETEIcean&quot;&gt;CETEIcean&lt;/a&gt;, and potentially &lt;a href=&quot;http://iiif.io/&quot;&gt;IIIF&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve begun this work on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huondauvergne.org&quot;&gt;Huon d’Auvergne Digital Archive&lt;/a&gt;) and I see a lot of promise in its use by others. I expect I will write more about the landscape, but the short version is: I think there’s still value in the TEI and not so much value in everyone learning XSLT to do something with TEI-encoded documents. I want to create an option for folks who don’t have their own developers but are willing to work through some good documentation. I also want to develop a new course on this topic (and maybe another course on something else). For a good dose of theory, I’ll be taking a scholarly editing course at Rare Book School next week. Finally, I’m hoping to use the proceedings for our local historical society as my demo text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I just want to make texts available online in their best possible form. I want this to be easy for scholars, but mostly I want more texts to make it to the public. I could say more, especially about my particular context, but for now let me leave you with a view of my summer office:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/office.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;laptop on table in outdoor setting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2019/06/03/sabbatical-plans.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2019/06/03/sabbatical-plans.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Born Digital Archives in the Undergraduate Classroom</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Alternate title: why blog about teaching when you can just publish a new article for every class?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to share this recent article in one of my favorite journals: Journal of Interactive Technology and Pedagogy. &lt;a href=&quot;https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/born-digital-archives-in-the-undergraduate-classroom/&quot;&gt;Born Digital Archives in the Undergraduate Classroom&lt;/a&gt; is a write-up of my first-year seminar taught in 2018. Through an educational partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive-it.org/&quot;&gt;Archive-It&lt;/a&gt;, students worked to create their own web archive on a topic of their choosing. It was a fun class! The article covers my methods for introducing a first-year audience to archival theory and digital preservation. It’s just a “View from the Field,” so if you’re looking for more detail, I suggest checking out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mackenziekbrooks.gitbooks.io/dh-180-born-digital/content/&quot;&gt;syllabus&lt;/a&gt;. I have no immediate plans to teach it again, but I hope it can inspire others to make use of born-digital archives in their own teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 15:19:19 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2019/03/18/born-digital-archives-article-published.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2019/03/18/born-digital-archives-article-published.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Teaching TEI to Undergraduates article published!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just wanted to drop in and mention the publication of my first real peer-reviewed article: “Teaching TEI to undergraduates: a case study in digital humanities curriculum” in the special issue of &lt;em&gt;College and Undergraduate Libraries&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tandfonline.com/eprint/DdAqRHI8gySCKnvtvmHy/full&quot;&gt;publisher&lt;/a&gt; // &lt;a href=&quot;https://repository.wlu.edu/handle/11021/33912&quot;&gt;open access&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case study describes two iterations of a Digital Humanities (DH) “Studio” course on scholarly text encoding as a model for a DH curriculum at a small liberal arts college. Designed to accompany a three-credit humanities course, the one-credit DH Studios are taught by library faculty. The paired courses share a final project — a digital edition of a short work of literature encoded in the Text Encoding Initiative. The DH Studio creates a methodology-focused environment for students to practice information and digital literacies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflection&quot;&gt;Reflection:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to teaching commitments and that vicious procrastination/perfectionism cycle, I left myself far too little time to write a twenty page article. There were definitely some bleary weekends and evenings in the month of January. I am a slow writer, even on a topic that is essentially just a report. Revisions were minor, so I can apparently produce decent work while bleary, but I hope someday to be able to work well without the pressure of deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one-credit “humanities lab” concept described in this case study is something that we bring up a lot in my DH/liberal arts circles. I wanted to document how the model worked for us in case it’s useful to others. I do still like the concept, but as the administrator says in &lt;em&gt;The History Boys&lt;/em&gt;, “Strange how even the most tragic turn of events generally resolve themselves into questions about the timetable.” Scheduling is hard!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These courses were my first real experiences teaching full courses. I feel like I have learned a lot since then! The inherent iteration is my favorite part of teaching. You have so many chances to make things better, from year to year or week to week. While I find perfectionism to be a problem when writing, I knew that it would be the death of me when teaching. While I tried to make good decisions, I also didn’t beat myself up if/when things didn’t go well. If you’re paying attention, you will learn something every time you’re in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, I taught three sections (4 students each) of DH 190. Each section was totally different and I had to learn to frame material differently based on the vibe of each group. It was a little like A/B testing in the classroom. Sections of four meant I could give each student individual attention, but I still felt pulled in too many directions, especially when dealing with OS/browser issues. Students worked in pairs, but I encouraged them to help each other when one had solved a problem first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t say what the future of this course will be. While undergraduates can “get” TEI, I’m not sure they need to. I could see reworking this course to focus on minimal editions (see Torrent’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://susannalles.com/materials/syllabi/MinimalEditions.html&quot;&gt;syllabus&lt;/a&gt;). Now that I feel capable of teaching git (thanks Brandon Walsh), I think the git/github/Jekyll/Ed stack might be more fun. The pairing of this course with an advanced French lit course meant that we were using TEI as a vehicle to close reading the course texts. Without the pairing, we could work to transcribe documents from Special Collections with students selecting the types of texts that interested them. We’ll see!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2017 08:02:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2017/07/20/teaching-tei-to-undergraduates.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2017/07/20/teaching-tei-to-undergraduates.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Shot Update</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a year and a half since I assumed liaison responsibilities to the English department at MPOW. I won’t claim to have blossomed into the world’s best liaison, but I have been teaching one-shot instruction sessions on a regular basis. If you’ve spent any time in the instruction/information literacy world, then you know that most librarians are not a fan of the one-shot session. I’ve been “victim” to all the usual complaints: bad timing, course materials aren’t shared, limited time, no pre/post assessment, late notice, no stakes in the assignment, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, I could spend more time cultivating my department to take these sessions more seriously. But after the chance to integrate information literacy concepts into full courses via our Digital Humanities curriculum, it makes more sense to invest my time in that form of pedagogy. I’m not going to stop accepting one-shot requests, but I am going to stop expecting more than is reasonable. What can I really accomplish in thirty minutes with first-year writing students? What are the most useful things for students to learn at this point in the semester?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started developing a one-shot presentation, I was fresh off of several meetings about the new ACRL Framework. I had just read David Weinberger’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/966459702&quot;&gt;Too big to know : rethinking knowledge now that the facts aren’t the facts, experts are everywhere, and the smartest person in the room is the room&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. This was all useful context, but I was overwhelmed by material to cover. I attempted to distill Weinberger’s book into a couple concepts that I could share with students, including: 1) filter failure as a mental model for information overload and 2) how the internet changed the storage and retrieval of information and knowledge gatekeepers. I used the “filter failure” idea to encourage the use of filters in whatever database students are using. I used the changing nature of information to explain some of the library’s (ancient in the eyes of students, and let’s be real, myself) organizational principles. I also tried to work in the “information has value” framework by making students guess our annual collections budget (I still do this. They are always blown away.). These concepts were useful for my own thinking, but I struggled to incorporate them into instruction in a non-prescriptive way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I had a spare morning before an afternoon one-shot and decided to redo my entire presentation. First, I reviewed results from a two-question survey I had administered to a few Writing 100 courses last year. The questions were: 1) What is the most confusing thing about the library and 2) What is the most confusing thing about research? Most of the responses to the first question related to how the library and the collection were organized. The answers to the second question were more useful. Students listed a range of concerns: how to get started, how to cite properly, what makes a good source, and my favorite, “I’m scared of plagiarism and getting kicked out.” From these 40+ responses, I determined the most frequently asked questions, sorted them to mirror the research process, then bookended them with some context-setting questions. The results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the academic library?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where do I start?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I know what keywords to use?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I go further?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What makes a good source?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I organize my research?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if I need more help?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized that the FAQ format would be a great way to attempt to encourage student participation. In my presentations, I try to solicit answers to all questions before volunteering my own. This gives students a chance to share knowledge they might have already gained through other classes or experiences. It is also a useful model for dealing with varying levels of student participation. Some classes are chatty and willing to ask/answer questions throughout, others are definitely not. I can also keep this template for upper-level students by modifying my answers for more in-depth research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I’ve used this new slidedeck in a few Writing 100 courses. The presentations feel smoother, more useful, and more interactive. I know I need to find a way to work in assessment, but it’s great to finally have a flexible structure for these class visits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.mackenziekbrooks.info/slides/slides-library-research-faq.html&quot; width=&quot;576&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 12:45:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2017/03/16/one-shot-update.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2017/03/16/one-shot-update.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Library-Faculty Partnerships Enrich Undergraduate Teaching at Washington and Lee</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;[Originally published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diglib.org/archives/11322/&quot;&gt;Digital Library Federation Contribute blog&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu&quot;&gt;DH @ W&amp;amp;L blog&lt;/a&gt;. Co-written with &lt;a href=&quot;https://bmw9t.github.io/&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt;, Digital Humanities Fellow.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wlu.edu&quot;&gt;Washington and Lee University (W&amp;amp;L)&lt;/a&gt; is excited to be a part of the Digital Library Federation’s efforts, particularly as they pertain to promoting digital humanities on liberal arts campuses. The digital humanities initiative at W&amp;amp;L has grown out of longstanding attempts to connect faculty and staff working in related areas across the university. Our primary goal is to foster communication and training among librarians and faculty at all levels of technical skill in the service of encouraging new approaches to digital pedagogy and research methodology. These efforts grow out of two overlapping groups: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/about/digital-humanities-working-group/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Working Group&lt;/a&gt;, a collective of faculty and staff across the university interested in the intersection of information technology and humanities research and teaching, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/about/dhat/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Action Team&lt;/a&gt;, a joint initiative by W&amp;amp;L’s Information Technology Services (ITS) and the University Library that provides day-to-day guidance and training on integrating digital methodologies into faculty teaching and research. By partnering library faculty and staff with teaching faculty, we believe that we can develop undergraduate pedagogy in a way that benefits all participants. We bring digital humanities to bear on a liberal arts context by encouraging faculty research with undergraduate partners, by using digital tools in the classroom as opportunities to promote digital literacy, and by offering new occasions for collaborative teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undergraduates stand to learn a great deal from working on digital humanities projects, and these students offer enormous energy and resources to their adopted teams. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huondauvergne.org/&quot;&gt;Huon d’Auvergne project&lt;/a&gt;, a digital edition being developed at W&amp;amp;L by Professor Stephen P. McCormick, library faculty, and inter-institutional collaborators, offers one such model for collaboration among faculty, students, and staff that collapses traditional pedagogical hierarchies. While students might begin to learn about the project in the classroom, after a semester course in textual encoding they are given the opportunity to work alongside their professor and digital humanities developers in an actual research setting. We encourage students to take ownership of their contributions to the project. Our students present at conferences, appear as co-authors on papers, and list project contributions on their CV. Through support from the office of the Dean of the College and The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, we stimulate such collaborations by offering competitive stipends to both the faculty and students involved. By further funding undergraduate research projects in digital humanities through a fellowship program, we provide training for students to explore their own interests with the same sort of support that we might offer humanities faculty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We carry our support of digital projects and tools in the classroom beyond logistics and mechanics, using them as opportunities to educate students about more traditional information literacy topics. Many of our librarians involved in work with classroom instruction began their careers in cataloging or systems librarianship, but our digital humanities efforts have created a space in which they can translate these experiences into outward-facing pedagogy in metadata, intellectual property, and digital preservation. These teaching opportunities generate collaborations with subject and instruction librarians who already possess extensive training in curriculum design and information literacy instruction. When working with Omeka, for example, our Digital Scholarship Librarian provides students training in digitization, metadata conventions, and sustainability. While the digitization of original material often falls outside the scope of semester-long Omeka projects, she still takes the time to discuss copyright, attribution, and the ethical and legal use of digital materials. These courses often receive joint visits by our Access Services Librarian and Instructional Design Specialist who offer workshops in visual literacy. By dividing labor among related faculty in such a way we leverage expertise in information literacy from a variety of angles and combine them in a rich curriculum for students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our efforts to disperse technical knowledge beyond early adopters, we have been experimenting with different models of collaborative teaching. One such model, the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/initiatives/curriculum/&quot;&gt;DH Studio&lt;/a&gt;,” involves pairing a traditional humanities course with a one-credit lab. The studio courses are taught by library faculty and give students dedicated time and expertise to learn and apply digital methodologies without sacrificing course content. We are also exploring more direct models of co-teaching in which course time and credits are extended to allow for “baked-in” digital methodology and course content. By partnering with French, journalism, and history professors, we have been able to offer courses in medieval French literature and textual encoding, multimedia storytelling and design, and text analysis approaches to histories of British scandal. Such hybrid courses offer students new avenues of study that educate the instructors as well. And by gearing digital assignments toward primary course objectives, we hope to show that digital humanities collaborations, far from detracting from disciplinary material, can actually challenge and enrich them. By working together, in the short term, digital humanities faculty gain disciplinary skills outside their normal area of expertise, and teaching faculty learn digital humanities skills and techniques in which they might not otherwise have training. In the long term, we aim for these same faculty members to develop the skill-sets necessary to teach these same courses and design new offerings without the same level of collaboration and support, allowing library faculty to further develop new courses themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see the library as the natural home for digital humanities initiatives on the liberal arts campus. The expertise of our faculty and staff in digital technologies and information literacy pedagogy, combined with our close relationships with ITS colleagues and concentration on the practical implications of digital scholarship, stands to enrich the undergraduate curriculum. We offer the library to our students as a space where they can meet faculty and staff as collaborators as well as educators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 11:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2016/02/12/library-faculty-partnerships.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2016/02/12/library-faculty-partnerships.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Search Everything</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During the weeks leading up to fall term, my institution puts on something we call “Fall Academy.” Organized by Academic Technologies, faculty and staff gather for various training, refresher, or orientation sessions on technology, pedagogy, and university policies or practices. It is awesome. And exhausting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, in addition to participating in our &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/2015/07/29/day-of-dh-at-fall-academy-2015/&quot;&gt;Day of DH&lt;/a&gt;, I led a session called “Search Everything.” Nominally this was about our using our discovery layer (Search Everything being the label we use on the library website), but I decided to take a broader approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resetting expectations was my main motivation for this talk. I’m afraid I may have come off too harsh or defensive, but I was not going to stand for any card catalog nostalgia. It’s a complex world out there for information seekers. “Too big to know” as David Weinberger says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My secondary motivation was to remind attendees that their students have almost always lived in a world where Google exists. I might be the youngest “professor” on campus, so sometimes I find myself in this role of Millennial ambassador or translator. I used this presentation to tell the “adults” about student research habits and challenges, primarily through data from &lt;a href=&quot;http://projectinfolit.org/&quot;&gt;Project Information Literacy&lt;/a&gt;. I also walked them through what I tell students about the very recent history of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope it was a useful talk. It was hard to prepare knowing that the audience would bring a wide range of experience. If nothing else, attendees learned to put search terms in quotes except in Google where you have to use Verbatim search, because Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.slides.com/mackenziekbrooks/search-everything/embed&quot; width=&quot;576&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 05:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2015/09/06/search-everything.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2015/09/06/search-everything.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ALA Annual 2015 + FAST</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Again with the time delay, but today is an out-of-office writing day and this blog post is my warm up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my third ALA Annual Conference and I think I’m finally getting the hang of things. I chose better sessions, spent and reserved energy appropriately, and finally brought a Bluetooth iPad keyboard for effective tweeting. I always seem to attend ALA in a transitional job state, and this visit was no different. As of July 1 (during ALA mind you), I am Digital Humanities Librarian at MPOW. I’m thrilled about the change, but it meant I needed to look outside of my normal ALCTS programming to build my schedule. I concentrated on anything with “linked data” in the title. Major points to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://alaac15.ala.org/node/28856&quot;&gt;Amber Billey and and Allison Jai O’Dell&lt;/a&gt; for convering the topic with enthusiasm and to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lib.montana.edu/~jason/talks/ala2015-linked-data-discovery.pdf&quot;&gt;Jason Clark&lt;/a&gt; for making a vendor session bearable. I supplemented my schedule with sessions from folks I know and trust, including Sarah Hovde talking about &lt;a href=&quot;http://alaac15.ala.org/node/29193&quot;&gt;cataloging education&lt;/a&gt; (turn[s out, some people actually get on the job cataloging training, how nice for them), Annie Pho on &lt;a href=&quot;http://alaac15.ala.org/node/28722&quot;&gt;#critlib&lt;/a&gt;, Erin Leach leading &lt;a href=&quot;http://alaac15.ala.org/node/29217&quot;&gt;Creative Ideas in Technical Services”&lt;/a&gt; and Eric Phetteplace (okay Eric was just my LITA Happy Hour buddy). I always try to check out one or two sessions from the big name speaker series, except somehow this year I missed Gloria Steinham and Nick Offerman. It’s nice to be reminded by someone famous that the work you’re doing is important and valued, even if most of their experience is with children’s librarians. It can be hard to sustain interest and enthusiasm for Monday sessions, but they ended up being the best of the whole conference thanks to an amazing talk by &lt;a href=&quot;http://ase.tufts.edu/crlr/team/wolf.htm&quot;&gt;Maryanne Wolf&lt;/a&gt; on deep reading in the digital age (for once, I was not enraged by this topic) and a stellar panel on contexutalizing Omeka exhibits by the folks behind the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ldhi.library.cofc.edu&quot;&gt;Lowcountry Digital History Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below you’ll find the slides from my presentation at the Faceted Subject Access Interest Group. It was a seven minute lightning talk and fortunately for you the slides below do not contain any of the jokes I made that fell flat in the room. The jist: we’ve spent the last two years implementing ArchivesSpace and we’ve made the decision to rely solely OCLC’s FAST headings for subject access points. The FAST headings complement ArchivesSpace’s SOLR indexing and they’re easy for Special Collections staff to apply. Since they’re available to download in several formats, it is fairly easy to get them into ArchivesSpace in batch. So far we’ve only added the topical headings. I want to add the geographic headings, but I have yet to learn enough XSLT to only pull out the Virginia headings. Because ArchivesSpace only displays subjects in the public interface when they’ve been attached to the record, it is not a problem to have 400k topical headings in the staff interface. We will delete headings that we encounter that seem totally irrelevant, though we’ve kept the “that’s what she said jokes” heading just in case. The panel went really well, the rest of the presentations can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;http://connect.ala.org/node/242549&quot;&gt;ALAConnect&lt;/a&gt;, though the audience really only seemed concerned with the FAST headings in their OPAC (the OPAC is dead, long live the OPAC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/mackenziekbrooks/speeding-up-archival-description-with-fast/embed&quot; width=&quot;576&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On location: San Francisco is amazing. I could never live there, in part because I think I’m done with urban life for now, but it was an ideal location for the conference and subsequent vacation. The convention center was easy to get around and had a lovely park on its roof, complete with fountains and ethnic fast food. There were plenty of places to eat and transportation was easy (I’m looking at you Chicago and Anaheim). I witnessed Pride and SCOTUS decision parties, again, way better than a Black Hawks rally (ahem Chicago). Brewster Kahle led a tour of the Internet Archive. Matthew Battles showed us &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i0RVSZ_yDjs&quot;&gt;“Toute la mémoire du monde”&lt;/a&gt; and Harvard verison, &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/116603551&quot;&gt;“Cold Storage.”&lt;/a&gt; There was a JMW Turner exhibit at the de Young. The weather, the parks, the plants, the food was all so great that it didn’t matter that I came down with a cold and had a terrible reaction to antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sometimes encounter librarians who have never been to ALA and it prompts me to consider why I continue to go. I don’t disagree that local/regional events are better in the cost/benefit department, but there is something about particpating on a national level that feels important. It gets you out of your insular library world, even if you all you do is complain about LibGuides with someone from another state. I’m not sure it shapes my professional identity so much as help it get in shape. And now that I’ve started to use a running metaphor, I think this post is over.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2015 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2015/08/03/ala-annual-2015-fast.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2015/08/03/ala-annual-2015-fast.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>#thatcampVA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend* I attended my second THATCamp. But before I talk about how wonderful it was, I want to spend a moment on my first THATCamp. It was the fall of 2011 and I had just finished up my MLIS program. I was working as a library assistant in a health sciences library, so my only outlet for DH-type work was a now-defunct project with my grad student boyfriend. Like most of grad school, it’s embarrassing to recall in much detail, but the theoretical goal was an online encyclopedia/wiki on “Literary Darwinism.”** In reality, it was a project that gave me an excuse to learn Drupal and gave some of my academically-minded friends a research project while they decided if grad school was actually a good idea. We took this project to THATCamp, proposed a session, and people showed up. Some of them even took us seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The culture of acceptance is one of the best parts of THATCamp. As someone with a “healthy” dose of imposter syndrome, conferences are often demoralizing in that still-so-many-things-to-learn way. But THATCamp produces these amazing positive “I’m learning so much!” feelings. There are a lot of reasons for this, but one of my favorites is the decentralization of authority. Experts and novices and everyone in between sit in the same circle to discuss a topic. You could be the most experienced person in the room at one session, or a total n00b at the next. Obviously, I’m not suggesting comparing yourself to others, but the interdisciplinary format encourages this kind of metacognitive assessment of your own skills and expertise. For instance, while we were discussing our project’s infrastructure, someone suggested that we use Weebly because it would be easy and Drupal is hard. I bristled at this in the moment. It was a reasonable suggestion, but I didn’t like the implication that I couldn’t handle Drupal. I knew I was capable of more than just a drag and drop interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward four years. I now have several years of professional experience as a metadata librarian, with at least one spent actively working in the DH world. I am comfortable participating (finally!). And I got to play the role of THATCamp veteran to the three colleagues who accompanied me. It was so gratifying to see their positive reactions to the experience. The romance languages faculty member was delighted to realize that a conference could be more than just listening to some academic read their paper. During the first session he met someone with considerable TEI experience and by the end of the day, we were in a TEI specific session having a meaningful and useful conversation. My librarian colleague went home inspired to ignite a few smoldering projects. We were able to bring a student along. She was brand new to DH, but totally held her own in every session. She wasn’t afraid to ask questions or share her opinion. We ended up in one session explaining how social media works to well-tenured professors. I hope it was a nice send-off for her, she’s now graduated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a final note, I read &lt;a href=&quot;http://libraryjuicepress.com/feminist-pedagogy.php&quot;&gt;Feminist Pedagogy for Library Instruction&lt;/a&gt; the same month as THATCamp Va, and the two complemented each other well. In addition to (or because of?) the aforementioned decentralized authority, women represented a large portion of the attendees, making it feel even less like a typical tech conference. Its open, productive, and collaborative qualities are all things I’d like to bring to my own teaching of technology, so it was helpful to actually experience those things in between terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So get yourself off to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://thatcamp.org/&quot;&gt;THATCamp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Please ignore the time gap between writing and publishing. I know it feels like decades in internet time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** Presented without comment: &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Darwinian_literary_studies&quot;&gt;the Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; on Literary Darwinism as written by Joseph Carroll, expert in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2015/05/31/thatcampva.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2015/05/31/thatcampva.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Website update</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve switched this site from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://getskeleton.com/&quot;&gt;Skeleton&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. No complaints with Skeleton, but I liked the promise of Jekyll: blog-aware and Markdown support. I enjoy hand coding, but I should probably devote that kind of energy into TEI. It took me two sittings to figure out exactly what I’m doing with Jekyll, but it makes more sense now. &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.tutsplus.com/articles/building-static-sites-with-jekyll--net-22211&quot;&gt;This tutorial&lt;/a&gt; helped, as did taking a minute to read through the .scss files instead of just blazing through with my CSS hammer. I’ve been taking notes in Markdown for the last few years, so being able to write in Markdown and a touch of YAML is nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still a lot to update. My CV does not reflect all the work I’ve done since starting at W&amp;amp;L. It won’t be long until I’ll have to start compiling my non-tenure-track-tenure-file. I need to gather material and write up the content for the projects page. But all that will have to wait for another chilly April afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2015 12:15:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/update/2015/04/25/website-update.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/update/2015/04/25/website-update.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
